## Dr. rer. nat. Jennifer E. Pollack

### Research Scientist | Statistical Software Developer

@ jpollacke@gmail.com

**\** +33 679887864

in linkedin.com/in/jennifer-eileen-pollack

github.com/jeipollack

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### Research Engineer, Astroparticle and Cosmology Laboratory, The French National Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS)

## 11/2020 - Present

Paris, France

## Software Developer for the European Space Agency's *Euclid* experiment

- Develop software and analysis chains for joint-processing and analysis of CCD images of galaxies and stars acquired from widefield ground-based and space-based telescopes
- Build and launch image pixel simulations to robustly test and assess scientific accuracy and performance of the data analysis software
- Monitor latest developments in image processing to improve photometric and astrometric calibration of the image data

## Senior Research Scientist, Institute for Computational Science, University of Zürich

**10/2017 - 9/2019** 

♀ Zürich, Switzerland

### Software and Science Project Lead for the European Space Agency's Euclid experiment

- Led a team of software developers and engineers in the production and maintenance of state-of-the-art science-ready data-products using terabytes of data and 1k CPU cores
- Provided better visualization of cosmological features in the spatial clustering patterns of galaxies using alternative mathematical representations for descriptive statistics
- Devised two novel methods to accurately estimate sample covariances from large volume datasets reducing computational expense by a factor of 1000
- Introduced new ways to tighten constraints on key model parameters, efficiently train and test machine learning algorithms, generate better forecasts, and explore physics of the early universe

# Senior Research Associate, Institute for Cosmology & Gravitation, University of Portsmouth

**#** 9/2014 - 8/2017

**♀** Portsmouth, United Kingdom

## Software Developer for the European Space Agency's *Euclid* and Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument Experiments

- Designed algorithm for high-level data analytical tools for the upcoming European Space Agency's Euclid galaxy survey (~600 million euros)
- Achieved 600% speed up of existing numerical code and made 55% more memory-efficient with results agreeing at machinelevel precision
- Analyzed the time-evolution of non-linear features in the clustering properties of galaxies using TB-size dataset from 200 numerical simulations to formulate accurate predictive models
- Developed robust methodology for testing nonlinear regression models for galaxy clustering using various summary statistics within the Bayesian framework

#### **ABOUT ME**

Innovative and resourceful research scientist and developer with a successful record in delivering computational and mathematical solutions in complex data analytics. I value teamwork, open-mindedness, and continuous learning in order to achieve operational excellence and high-end results.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Ph.D. in Astronomy, magna cum laude University of Bonn

M.Sc. in Astrophysics University of Bonn

B.A. in Physics New College of Florida

**1** 8/2002 - 5/2006

Sarasota, FL, USA

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

#### Programming/Query Languages

Python, Fortran, Unix shell scripting, high-performance computing, OpenMP, SQL

#### Software Packages & DevOps Tools

Jupyter Notebook, Numpy, Scipy, Pandas, Seaborn, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, Keras, TensorFlow, Lagent, Matlab, Mathematica, Doxygen, Git, Redmine, Oracle VirtualBox

#### Data Analysis

Data mining, Data compression methods, Probability, Statistics, Time- and Spatialseries analysis, Hyper-parameter tuning, Cross-Validation, Machine Learning

### Technical Writing

Writing, Proofreading, Software Design Documentation, Software Tests & Validation Plan, Software User Manuals, & Tutorials

#### **LANGUAGES**

English (Native) Spanish (C1) German (B1) French (B1)

### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Teaching Assistant, Argelander Institut für Astronomie, University of Bonn

■ Bonn, Germany

 Supervised problem sessions for Advanced data analysis and Bayesian statistics at the Master level

### **RESEARCH EXPERIENCE**

#### Graduate Research Assistant, University of Bonn

**1**/2011 - 10/2015

₱ Bonn, Germany

#### Dissertation: Cosmological Investigations with the Bispectrum

- Developed a new approach for modelling galaxy clustering using higher-order moments of the total matter density field
- Tested new model by computing and analyzing auto- and crosspolyspectra using galaxy catalogs extracted from 200 cosmological N-body simulations
- Applied statistical methods for Poisson processes, estimation of covariances, Bayesian inference, and likelihood sampling to accurately constrain model parameters

#### Graduate Research Assistant, University of Bonn

**10/2009 - 11/2010** 

P Bonn, Germany

## Master Thesis: Matter & Halo Bispectrum: Probing Large-Scale Halo Bias

- Conducted a study of non-linear regression models of the clustering properties of dark matter haloes using measurements of third-order connected correlation functions from 40 cosmological numerical N-body simulations
- Examined and compared various data modelling methods: bootstrapping, jack-knife sampling, PCA, Frequentist and Bayesian model selection

#### **FURTHER EDUCATION**

Google Tech Learning Series Workshop

Google, Completed on 2/8/2021

**Detector Modelling Workshop** 

European Southern Observatory, Completed on 16/6/2021

Deep Learning Specialization by deeplearning.ai

Coursera, Certificate earned on 13/2/2020

Data Wrangling, Analysis and AB Testing with SQL by UC Davis

Coursera, Completed on 20/11/2019

Machine Learning with Python by IBM

Coursera, Certificate earned on 14/10/2019

Machine Learning by Stanford University

Coursera, Certificate earned on 12/9/2019

Databases and SQL for Data Science by IBM

Coursera, Certificate earned on 10/9/2019

Machine Learning for High Energy Physics - a mini course **University of Zürich**, Completed on 5/2/2019

#### **VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE**

Programming Tutorial Creator, Orlando Lady Developers Meetup (remote)

## 10/2021-current

Orlando, FL

Host: Google AI Cloud Study Jam, AI Camp & Google AI Workshop

**12/2019** 

♥ Zürich, CH

Staff Representative in the Mathematics and Natural Sciences Department, University of Zürich

**5/2018-9/2019** 

♥ Zürich, CH

Science Demo: "Cosmic Expansion of Space", Stargazing Live Event

**#** 1/2017

Portsmouth, UK

Public Talk: "The Universe on the Grandest Scales", Pint of Science Event

**∰** 5/2016

**♀** Portsmouth, UK

Q&A: "Ask the Expert-Dark Matter", Stargazing Live Event

**#** 1/2016

Portsmouth, UK

#### **SELECTED TALKS**

**BK Function Galaxy Clustering Software**, Euclid Consortium Annual Meeting

**#** 6/2019

♥ Helsinki, FI

Computation of the Bispectrum Redshift-Space Multipoles, Euclid Joint LE3-SWG-GC Science Meeting

**∰** 2/2018

Nice, FR

Probing Cosmology with the Galaxy Bispectrum, California Institute of Technology

**11/2017** 

Pasadena, CA, USA

Cosmological Investigations with the Bispectrum. UK-Euclid Meeting

**12/2015** 

**♀** Edinburgh, GB

A new method to measure galaxy bias, Workshop on Galaxy Bias, ICTP

**10/2013** 

▼ Trieste, IT

#### **EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES**

#### **Athletics**

Aerobics, Basketball, Boxing, Dancing, HIIT workouts, Hiking and Jogging

#### Travel

Architecture, Arts, Culture, International cuisine, and Nature

#### **Hobbies**

Baking, Cooking, Gardening, Meditation, Music, and Reading